<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="tei_news.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="aa.18631107.4">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">"Buried With His Niggers"</title>
                <title type="sub">a machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor role="co-editor">R. J. Weir</editor>
                <editor role="co-editor">Elizabeth Lorang</editor>
                <editor role="assistant">Kristen Treen</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>transcription and encoding</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="kt">Kristen Treen</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="bw">R. J. Weir</persName>
                    <persName xml:id="el">Elizabeth Lorang</persName>
                </respStmt>                    
            </titleStmt>        
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="file">aa.18631107.4</idno>                        
                <idno type="edition">cwnewspaperpoetry</idno>                 
                <authority>Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing</authority>                 
                <address>
                    <addrLine>http://www.scholarlyediting.org</addrLine>
                </address>                 
                <publisher>Association for Documentary Editing</publisher>                 
                <publisher>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</publisher>                 
                <distributor>                     
                    <name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>                     
                    <address> 		                
                        <addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine> 		                
                        <addrLine>University of Nebraska–Lincoln</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>http://cdrh.unl.edu</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </distributor>
                <date>2012</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                        <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/). Derivatives must be credited to R. J. Weir and Elizabeth Lorang, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>                 
                <title level="j">Scholarly Editing: The Annual of the Association for Documentary Editing</title>                 
                <respStmt>                     
                    <resp>editor</resp>                     
                    <name xml:id="ag">Amanda Gailey</name>                 
                </respStmt>                 
                <respStmt>                     
                    <resp>editor</resp>                     
                    <name xml:id="awj">Andrew Jewell</name>                 
                </respStmt>                 
                <idno type="vol">34</idno>                 
                <idno type="ISSN">2167-1257</idno>             
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct xml:id="poem">
                    <analytic>                        
                        <author ref="#ebs">Elizabeth B. Sedgwick</author>
                        <title level="a">"Buried With His Niggers"</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title xml:id="paper" level="j">The Anglo-African</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <date xml:id="issue_date" when="1863-11-07">7 November 1863</date>                    
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="pp">[4]</biblScope>                    
                    </monogr>
                    <note type="repository">The microfilm copy used for transcription was loaned by Northwestern University.</note>
                    
                </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct xml:id="issue">               
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j" sameAs="#paper"/>
                        <imprint>
                            <date sameAs="#issue_date"/>                  
                        </imprint>              
                    </monogr>                   
                </biblStruct>                        
            </sourceDesc>       
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc> 
            <p>This electronic text is a semi-diplomatic transcription of the source text. Hyphenation, punctuation, variant spellings, and errors present in the source text have been retained. The transcription does not attempt to capture all aspects of the original formatting or layout.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <persName xml:id="ebs">Sedgwick, Elizabeth Buckminster Dwight, 1801-1864</persName>
                <persName xml:id="rh">Hamilton, Robert</persName>
                <persName xml:id="th">Hamilton, Thomas</persName>
                <date when="1863">1863</date>
            </creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en-US">modern American English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <classCode scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov">
                    <term>African American soldiers</term>
                    <term>Burial--Social aspects--United States--History--19th century</term>
                    <term>Fort Wagner (S.C.)</term>
                    <term>Shaw, Robert Gould, 1837-1863</term>
                    <term>United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Religious aspects</term>
                </classCode>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2013-03-02" who="#el">made copyediting changes</change>
            <change when="2013-02-24" who="#el">revised note about NAS printing</change>
            <change when="2013-01" who="#el">revised transcription and encoding to address errors and inconsistencies; updated editorial notes</change>
            <change when="2012-11" who="#awj">added Scholarly Editing info to TEI header</change>
            <change when="2012-10-14" who="#el">encoded; added and encoded editorial notes</change>
            <change when="2012-10-01" who="#kt">variants noted</change>
            <change when="2012-09-30" who="#el">checked</change>
            <change when="2012-09-03" who="#el">created</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <facsimile corresp="#issue">
        <surface xml:id="pp1">
            <graphic url="aa.18631107.pp1.jpg"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp2">
            <graphic url="aa.18631107.pp2.jpg"/>   
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp3">
            <graphic url="aa.18631107.pp3.jpg"/>
        </surface>
        <surface xml:id="pp4">
            <graphic url="aa.18631107.pp4.jpg"/> 
            <zone xml:id="pp4_cropped" corresp="#poem">
                <graphic url="aa.18631107.pp4_cropped.jpg"/>
            </zone>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    
    <text corresp="#poem #pp4_cropped">
        
        <body>
            
            <lg type="poem">
                
                <head type="main" subtype="authorial" rend="center">"BURIED WITH HIS NIGGERS."<note type="editorial" resp="#bw #el">This poem also appeared in the <title level="j">National Anti-Slavery Standard</title> of <ref target="nas.18631031.4a">October 31, 1863</ref>. The text of the poem is the same in both printings. Although the <title level="j">Anglo-African</title> credited the <title level="j">Evening Post</title>, the poem likely was reprinted from the <title level="j">Standard</title>.</note></head>
                
                <note type="authorial">"When the body of Col. <emph rend="smallcaps">Robert G. Shaw</emph><note type="editorial" resp="#bw #el"><p>Robert Gould Shaw (1837&#8211;July 18, 1863) was colonel of the Fifty-Fourth Massachusetts Regiment, the first regiment of African American volunteers raised in the North, authorized in late January 1863 and mustered into the US service on May 13. Governor John A. Andrew of Massachusetts received War Department authorization to raise the first Northern regiment of African American volunteers in January 1863. Determined to form a model regiment, Andrew took care to select advisers, officers, and recruiters with antislavery convictions or connections; he offered Shaw the regiment's colonelcy at the end of January, on the basis of the young captain's military record and his wealthy family's influence in reform circles. Shaw turned Andrew down; he did not have abolitionist principles to trump his strong attachment to the Second Massachusetts Infantry. His mother persuaded him to think again.</p>
                    <p>Black leaders called on men to enlist and thereby seize their "golden opportunity" and "first best chance" to establish an undeniable claim to the full rights of American citizens (Frederick Douglass, "Men of Color, to Arms!" reprinted in the <title level="j">Anglo-African</title>, March 7, 1863, [2]; editorial, <title level="j">Anglo-African</title>, March 7, 1863, [2]). The Fifty-Fourth quickly filled with men "from virtually every black community in the North" (Donald Yacovone, <title level="m">A Voice of Thunder: A Black Soldier's Civil War</title> [Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1998], 31). A number of the new recruits would provide the <title level="j">Anglo-African</title> and the <title level="j">Christian Recorder</title> with correspondence from the front during their term of service. Both titles served as a channel of communication between distant volunteers and the folks at home.</p>
                    <p>Under Shaw's command, the regiment took shape at Camp Meigs in Readville, Massachusetts. On May, 28, 1863, after weeks of training, the men paraded through Boston's cheering streets and then embarked on the steamer <name type="ship">De Molay</name>, bound for South Carolina's Sea Islands and the theater of war. On July 18, 1863, Shaw and the Fifty-Fourth courageously led a frontal attack on Morris Island's (South Carolina) Fort Wagner. Their bravery could not compensate for General Quincy Gillmore's poor planning; the assault failed, and 272 members of the regiment were killed, wounded, or taken prisoner (Russell Duncan, ed., <title level="m">Blue-Eyed Child of Fortune: The Civil War Letters of Col. Robert Gould Shaw</title> [Athens: University of Georgia Press, 1999], 52). Northern newspapers reported that Fort Wagner's Confederate garrison had buried Shaw in a mass grave with his men. Abolitionists reinterpreted the Confederate gesture of contempt as a mark of distinction. Shaw's parents made known their wish that his body should not be disturbed: "We would not have his body removed from where it lies surrounded by his brave &#38; devoted soldiers, if we could accomplish it by a word" (letter dated August 3, 1863, quoted in Duncan, 54).</p></note> was asked of <lb/>those rebels in the midst of whom he fell, it was replied: <lb/>"He is buried with his niggers."</note>
                
                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l><emph rend="smallcaps">Buried</emph> with a band of brothers<note type="editorial" resp="#bw #el">Perhaps an allusion to Shakespeare's <title level="m">King Henry V</title>. Before the battle of Agincourt, Henry rallies his outnumbered soldiers with the promise of immortal fame and a vision of fraternity; each year, proud survivors will keep the battle's anniversary and pass on the story. The king also declares that a battlefield bond will elevate every soldier to noble rank, and thus level the feudal hierarchy: "We few, we happy few, we band of brothers. / For he today that sheds his blood with me / Shall be my brother; be he ne'er so vile, / This day shall gentle his condition" (act 4, scene 3, <title level="m">Henry V</title>, ed. T. W. Craik [London: Arden Shakespeare, 1995]).</note></l>
                    <l rend="indented1">Who for him would fain have died;</l>
                    <l>Buried with the gallant fellows</l>
                    <l rend="indented1">Who fell fighting by his side.</l>
                </lg>
                
                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Buried with the men God gave him,</l>
                    <l rend="indented1">Those whom he was sent to save;</l>
                    <l>Buried with the martyred heroes,</l>
                    <l rend="indented1">He has found an honored grave.</l>
                </lg>
                
                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Buried where his dust so precious</l>
                    <l rend="indented1">Makes the soil a hallowed spot;</l>
                    <l>Buried where, by Christian patriot,</l>
                    <l rend="indented1">He shall never be forgot.</l>
                </lg>
                
                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Buried in the ground accursed,</l>
                    <l rend="indented1">Which man's fettered feet have trod;</l>
                    <l>Buried where his voice still speaketh,</l>
                    <l rend="indented1">Appealing for the slave to God.</l>
                </lg>
                
                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Fare thee well, thou noble warrior,</l>
                    <l rend="indented1">Who in youthful beauty went</l>
                    <l>On a high and holy mission,</l>
                    <l  rend="indented1">By the God of battles sent.</l>
                </lg>
                
                <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Chosen of Him, "elect and precious,"<note type="editorial" resp="#bw #el">Possibly a reference to the contemporary hymn "Saint of God, Elect and Precious," which celebrated the martyrdom of St. Stephen. A Christ-parallel is also implicit: see 1 Peter 2:6, "Behold, I lay in Zion a chief corner stone, elect, precious: and he that believeth on him shall not be confounded."</note></l>
                    <l rend="indented1">Well didst thou fulfil thy part:</l>
                    <l>When thy country "counts her jewels,"</l>
                    <l rend="indented1">She shall wear thee on her heart.</l>
                </lg>
                
            </lg>
            
            
            <dateline>Lemnot, Mass.</dateline>
            <byline rend="right"><emph rend="smallcaps">Elizabeth B. Sedgwick.</emph><note type="editorial" resp="#bw #el"><p>Elizabeth Buckminster Dwight Sedgwick (1801&#8211;1864), sister-in-law of Catharine Maria Sedgwick, was headmistress of a girls' school in Lenox, Massachusetts, from 1829 until 1859. Like Robert Gould Shaw, Sedgwick's son William served in the Second Massachusetts Infantry. He was mortally wounded at the Battle of Antietam (September 17, 1862) and died almost two weeks later; Sedgwick and her daughter nursed him in the days before his death ("Charles Sedgwick Papers, 1813&#8211;1908: Guide to the Collection," Massachusetts Historical Society).</p>
                <p>Shaw knew the Sedgwick family. In a letter dated March 17, 1863, he told his mother that he had passed a pleasant visit at Lenox with "Mrs. Charles and [Mrs.] Willie Sedgwick" (Elizabeth and her daughter-in-law, Louisa) and that he had told them "a great deal" about William. Elizabeth he described as "one of the most patriotic women I have seen" (Russell Duncan, ed., <title level="m">Blue-Eyed Child of Fortune: The Civil War Letters of Col. Robert Gould Shaw</title> [Athens: University of Georgia Press, 1999], 308&#8211;9).</p></note></byline>
            <note type="newspaper-editorial">&#8212;<title level="j" rend="italic">Evening Post</title>.<note type="editorial" resp="#bw #el">The <title level="j">New York Evening Post</title>, founded by Alexander Hamilton in 1801. William Cullen Bryant (1794&#8211;1878) began to write for the title in 1826, having struggled to make a living as a poet; by 1830 he was the <title level="j">Post</title>'s editor-in-chief, and the daily's financial prospects looked good (Allan Nevins, <title level="m">The Evening Post: A Century of Journalism</title> [New York: Russell and Russell, 1968], 134-136). Committed to Free Soil principles, Bryant severed the <title level="j">Post</title>'s connection with the Democratic Party in response to the Kansas-Nebraska Act (1854) and backed the fledgling Republican Party in 1856. He threw his weight behind Lincoln's presidential campaign in 1860. Although the <title level="j">Post</title> remained staunchly Republican throughout the war, Bryant did not shrink from criticizing Lincoln's policies. The <title level="j">Post</title> "shared with the <title level="j">Tribune</title> the advocacy of what came to be called the 'radical' Republican doctrines during the Civil War&#8212;namely, emancipation, the need of strong and swift military measures, and the removal of pro-slavery and Democratic leaders from the government and army" (Frank Luther Mott, <title level="m">American Journalism: A History of Newspapers in the United States Through Twenty Years, 1690&#8211;1940</title> [New York: Macmillan, 1941], 5:344).</note></note>
            
        </body>
    </text>
    
</TEI>

